あきらめるな！ 男たちよ!!
[Thursday Night Movie Theater
right after these messages!!]
Men, don't give up!
[Will our savior come to this dying planet?]
♪♪～
＜ｶｲ:それは 突如
私たちの足元から顔を出した＞
It...
suddenly appeared beneath our feet...
♪♪～
＜ｶｲ:それが何なのか
生物であるのか➡
What were they? Were they living creatures? Were they man-made?
造られたものなのか それとも➡
Or was it something else entirely?
それ以外のものなのか…｡
それを理解する前に
私たちの半分は消滅した＞
Before we could find out...
half of us were wiped out.
＜ｶｲ:分裂し すさまじい勢いで
増殖する それらは➡
It split and multiplied at an incredible rate.
瞬く間に地上を侵食｡
It instantly covered the world. By the time we figured out what it was...
それが 何なのか理解したとき➡
この星はもう
私たちのものじゃなくなっていた｡
The planet was no longer ours.
私たちが知りえた情報は
ただ一つ…｡
The only thing we learned...
あれは 生物でも
造られたものでもなく➡
was that it was neither alive nor man-made. It was "Despair" itself.
絶望そのものだということ｡
私たちは このままじゃ
絶滅するということだけだった＞
We were on the brink of annihilation.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)ここか…
来ますかね？ 救世主様｡
So this is the place.
Do you think The Savior will come?
(ｶｲ)来てくれなきゃ滅ぶだけだ！
If he doesn't come, we'll be destroyed.
(ｶｲ)この星が滅ぶといっても
死ぬのは 私とお前だけだがな｡
Not just the planet, but us too.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)おいおい地下には まだまだ
人間が生存してるでしょうが｡
Come on. There are humans still living underground.
(ｶｲ)戦うことを放棄し
地上をﾔﾂらに明け渡し➡
They've given up fighting and left the surface to "it."
暗い土の中で
震えるだけの連中なんて➡
They're just trembling in the dark soil.
墓場の腐った死体と同じだ｡
Just like rotting corpses in a cemetery.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)ﾌﾝ 隊長殿は酷だねぇ｡
Captain, that's cruel.
女 子供にも
あんなﾊﾞｹﾓﾉと戦えと？
Are you saying that women and children should fight monsters?
王国軍をたった12時間で
壊滅させた連中だぜ！
It destroyed the Royal Armed Forces in just twelve hours.
(ｶｲ)壊滅はしていない！
まだ 私とお前がいるだろう!!
It hasn't been destroyed. You and I are still here.
人は それぞれ
己に見合った敵と戦っている｡
Everyone fights the enemies that suit them.
女 子供といえど
やれることはある｡
Even women and children have things they can do. We do, too.
もちろん 私たちにもな｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)我々のやれることは
たった二人で地上に残り➡
Like remain on the surface and partake in guerrilla warfare?
ｹﾞﾘﾗ戦ですか…
身がもちませんな｡
We won't be able to keep that up. I hope our savior gets here quickly.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)早いとこ 救世主殿に
お越しいただきたいものです｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)宇宙を駆ける
伝説の掃除屋だか➡
I'm not sure if he's the legendary space-traveling janitor, or the strongest alien buster...
最強の えいりあんばすたーだか
知らねえが➡
一個人が
一国の存亡を左右するほどの➡
But I doubt he has the power to determine the fate of a country by himself.
力を有するなんぞ
眉唾もんですがね｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)たとえ もし
その伝説の救世主様が➡
Even if that legendary savior did exist...
本当に存在したとして➡
そんな大物が
国家も軍隊も瓦解し➡
The nation and the army have already collapsed.
何の恩賞も期待できない➡
Do you think such a person would come to the aid of two volunteer soldiers who can't offer any reward?
たった二人の
義勇軍の救援になど➡
来てくれるもんですかね？
来なければ
私とお前が死ぬだけだ！
If he doesn't come, you and I will just die.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)隊長 ｵﾚが死ねば➡
Captain, if I die, my wife and children underground will die, too.
地下の嫁さんも子供も
野垂れ死にますよ｡
(ｶｲ)保険がおりるだろう｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)絶対 ｱﾝﾀとなんか➡
They'll get insurance, right?
I won't ever commit suicide with you.
心中しねえ…｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)隊長殿！ 来ました!!
Captain, it's here!
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)
救世主じゃなくて お迎えが！
It isn't the savior. It's a welcoming party.
しかたねえ！
ｵﾚが ひきつけますんで➡
Oh well. I'll distract them.
女 子供は さっさと帰って➡
Women and children should leave...
地下で
掃除 洗濯でもしててください｡
and clean up the underground.
ｲﾜﾉﾌ！
Ivanov...
I said I had no intention of committing suicide with you, captain.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)隊長と心中なんざ
ご免こうむると言ったんです！
ふざけるな！
No way!
上官の命令は絶対だ！
勝手に死ぬことは許さん!!
A superior officer's orders are absolute.
I won't let you die without my permission!
上官どころか 軍隊自体
もう ありゃしませんよ！
We don't have any superior officers, let alone an army!
＜ｶｲ:絶望に
うちひしがれることがあっても➡
Even if I'm crushed by despair,
we must never forget...
忘れてはいけない｡
陽あるところに影があるように➡
Where there is light, there are shadows and where there are shadows, there is light.
影あるところには
陽があることを｡
絶望の色が濃ければ濃いほど
そこには…＞
No matter how dark the despair, there is...
(爆発音)
うぅっ…｡
♪♪～
...hope shining bright!
＜ｶｲ:強く輝く
希望があることを…＞
♪♪～
Sorry to keep you waiting.
(星海坊主)待たせて悪かったな｡
(星海坊主)ｵﾚを呼んだ
救世軍ってのはｱﾝﾀらかい？
Are you the volunteer army that called me?
＜ｶｲ:長く暗い闇に閉ざされていた
私たちの星は…＞
Our planet, which has long been trapped in darkness...
(星海坊主)
あぁ 紹介 遅れてすまん｡
Oh, sorry. I haven't introduced myself.
＜ｶｲ:ようやく
まばゆい陽光を浴びよう…＞
...has finally seen the dazzling light of dawn...
ｵﾚの名は… 星海坊主！
My name is...
Umibozu.
ん？ どうした？
What's wrong? Is there something on my face?
ｵﾚの顔に何かついてるか？
いや…｡
あの 別に…｡
No.
It's nothing...
ﾂﾞﾗだ…｡
星海坊主 ﾂﾞﾗだ…｡
A toupee.
Umibozu is wearing a toupee.
ｲﾜﾉﾌ ﾀﾞﾒだ！
そんなにｼﾞｯと見つめたら…｡
Ivanov, don't stare at it like that.
気づかないふりをするんだ…
見てみぬふりをするんだ｡
Act like you don't notice it.
Pretend you don't know.
この星の命運が
あの男にかかっているんだぞ！
The fate of our planet depends on this man.
いや しかし隊長… あれ…｡
Well... But captain... That...
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)完全にﾊﾞﾚﾊﾞﾚだよ！
It's totally obvious... It's even sliding off...
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)完全にずれて あれ
頭の上にﾅｲﾛﾝのってるだけだよ｡
There's just nylon on his head.
(ｶｲ)ｲﾜﾉﾌ… おさえろ！
あの強さを見ただろう!!
Ivanov, hold it in. You saw his strength, right?
もう私たちの希望は
この男しかいない！
That man...
is our only hope.
(ｶｲ)ﾂﾞﾗだけど最強なんだ！
Even if he's wearing a toupee, he's invincible.
恥をかかせて帰られたら
終わりだぞ！
It's all over if we embarrass him and he leaves.
ｵｯｹｰ 大丈夫 うまくやるさ！
こんな任務➡
O-Okay. It's all right. I can do this...
This mission is way easier than that Apache landing operation five years ago.
５年前のｱﾊﾟｯﾁ上陸作戦に比べれば
たやすい任務だ！
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)ま… 待ってたぜ
星海坊主の旦那！
W-We've been waiting for you, Umibozu-san.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)まさか
生ける伝説に出会えるとはな｡
I never thought I'd get to meet a living legend.
(ｶｲ)本当に来てくれるとは…
ご協力に 感謝する！
We never thought you'd really come.
I'm grateful for your help.
私は ｶｲ！ こっちは ｲﾜﾉﾌだ｡
I'm Kai.
This is Ivanov. Pleased to meet you.
よろしく！
I never expected this country to change so much in just three years.
しかし たった３年で 国が
こんなに変わってしまうとは…｡
いったい 何があった？
What in the world happened?
《ｲﾜﾉﾌ:ｱﾝﾀこそ 何があったら
そんな状態になるんだよ》
What made your head change so much?
(ｶｲ)３年前 地中から
あの巨大な黒い球体が現れた｡
Three years ago, a giant black sphere erupted from the ground.
[Note: A similar plot device was used in the anime Space Pirate Captain Harlock.]
その球体から 次々と
無数の球体が生まれ➡
Countless spheres grew from it and it rapidly covered the surface of the world.
瞬く間に
地上を占拠してしまったんだ｡
国の全人口の半分が
すでにﾔﾂらの餌食に…｡
Half of this country's population has fallen victim to it.
ｵﾚたちの軍も必死に戦ったが➡
Our army desperately fought it,
激しい戦いの末
ほぼ壊滅しちまった｡
but after a bald battle, we were almost completely wiped out.
(星海坊主)えっ ﾊｹﾞ？
Huh? Bald?
Huh? B...No, I said, "bold battle." You're mistaken. No, no, no.
えっ？
いや 激しい戦いって言ったの！
違うよ！ いやいや… 違うよ
そういうんじゃないよ!!
You're mistaken. It's not like that.
えっ？ そういうんじゃないって
どういうんじゃないの？
Huh? If it's not, then what is it?
いや だからﾊｹﾞじゃなくて
激しいって…｡
I told you, I said "bold," not "bald"...
Hey! This time, you said "bald." You called me bald just now.
今こそ ﾊｹﾞっつった！
ﾊｹﾞって言ったよなぁ 今｡
いやいや…
今のは違うじゃないっすか！
No, no, no. I didn't do that.
いや 別にいいけどね｡
Well, I don't mind. I'm not bald... I have a head full of hair...
ｵﾚ ﾊｹﾞてないし ﾌｻﾌｻだし…
別にいいけど！
I don't mind, but people who are bald don't like bad jokes like that.
でも ﾊｹﾞてる人にとっては
あんま いい気分じゃないよね｡
そういう悪ふざけって…｡
謝れば？ 全国のﾊｹﾞの人に｡
Apologize to all the bald people in the country.
《ｲﾜﾉﾌ:ﾒﾁｬﾒﾁｬ
ﾃﾞﾘｹｰﾄなんですけど…｡
He's so sensitive. This man's feelings are like glass.
ｶﾞﾗｽ細工のｵｯｻﾝだよ！
ﾊｹﾞもの取り扱い注意だ》
I've got to be careful about words that sound like "bald."
すみませんでした！
I-I'm very sorry...
Why?! If he's so sensitive, why does he wear such a bad toupee?!
《ｲﾜﾉﾌ:なんで!?
なんで こんな敏感なくせに➡
あんな 鈍感なﾂﾞﾗ
かぶってんだよ!?》
It's a bit odd for you to apologize to me.
別に ｵﾚに謝られても
あれですけどね～！
I have a head full of hair.
ﾌｻﾌｻだから ｵﾚは…｡
まっ もういいや｡
Well, that's fine. Anyway, there's no point in arguing, so let's get going.
(星海坊主)とりあえず
しゃべってても なんだから➡
行くとこ 行こうぜ｡
Are we riding in this?
(星海坊主)これ 乗ればいいのか？
I wonder if it's going to rain tomorrow...
明日は 雨かな～？
ｲﾔなんすよね～｡
I hate that... I have nowhere to hang my laundry...
洗濯物 干すとこ なくて…｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)いきなり 地雷 踏んだよ
あの ｵｯｻﾝ…｡
He totally stepped into that one! We didn't see it. We didn't see anything.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)見てませんから…｡
ﾎﾞｸらは 一切 何も見てませんから｡
(ｶｲ)そろそろ いいだろうか…？
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)どうせだったら➡
I wonder if it's all right now.
We should give him time to put it on properly.
きっちり ｾｯﾄしてもらったほうが
いいでしょう｡
Then we won't have to worry about how bad it looks.
あの頭で うろうろされたら
気ぃ遣って しゃあねえ｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)もう少し 待ちましょうか？
Let's wait a little longer.
《ｲﾜﾉﾌ:なんで ｾｯﾄしたのに
さっきより 不自然なんだよ～！
Why does it look even more unnatural after he fixed it?
What's the meaning of this?
What was he thinking?
どういうことだ!?
どこ 目指してんだ あの ｵｯｻﾝ！
どんな髪形に なりたいんだよ～！
What kind of hair style is he after?!
いや おかしいって！ それ 絶対！
もう 直視できねえよ～！
No, this is definitely weird!! I can't look directly at him anymore.
ｶﾂﾗが
ｶﾂﾗの意味を なしてないもの！
His toupee has lost all purpose!!
It's obvious he's bald now!!
ﾊｹﾞ 丸出しだもの～！
Captain, are we going to take him like this?
隊長…
これで 連れていくんですか～？
This is bad.
やばいよ… これ やばいよ！》
This is really bad.
♪♪～
Everyone, listen up!!
みんな～！ 聞いてくれ～!!
(ｶｲ)こんな 汚いｼｪﾙﾀｰに➡
Why not put an end to living like moles in this filthy shelter?!
もぐらのように
引きこもり 暮らすのは➡
もう やめにしないか！
"It" has taken the surface from us, and we've lived for three years in humiliation!
ﾔﾂらに 地上を奪われ
屈辱の日々を過ごすこと ３年！
決起のときは 来た～！
The time to rally together is now!!
私たち 救世軍は➡
Our volunteer army has managed to summon the help of an invincible hero.
万夫不当の 英雄の力を
借りることに 成功した｡
We've got the heroic living legend Umibozu!!
生ける伝説…
英雄 星海坊主殿の力を!!
♪♪～
ｹｯ！
また ｶｲの演説が 始まったぜ｡
Tsk! Kai's blabbering off her speeches again.
あの 星海坊主が
こんなところ 来るわけねえだろ！
There's no way that Umibozu would come here.
誰だ？ あの 変な頭｡
Who's that man with the strange head?
Where did you get that faker?
どっから 連れてきたんだ？
あんな ﾆｾﾓﾉ！
誰の頭が ﾆｾﾓﾉだ!? ｺﾗ～!!
Whose head are you calling fake?!
言ってません！
誰も そんなこと 言ってません！
They didn't say that!! No one said that!! Captain, stop him!!
隊長～！ 止めてくれ～!!
彼の力が あれば➡
With his help, we can be victorious!!
必ずや 我々は
勝利を 手にすることができる！
(ｶｲ)みんな お願いだ！
一緒に 立ち上がろう！
Everyone, please, let's work together!
(ｶｲ)地上を… この星を…➡
The surface... This planet...
自らの手で 守るんだ～!!
We will defend it ourselves!!
Mom, you're only carrying sis...that's not fair.
お母さ～ん｡
お姉ちゃんばっかり ｽﾞﾙい～！
誰の頭が ｽﾞﾙｽﾞﾙだ～!!
Bare?! Whose head is bare?!
だ～ か～ ら～！
違うって 言ってんだろうが～!!
I told you, you're hearing things!!
It's a toupee!! He's wearing a toupee!!
ﾂﾞﾗだ～!! ｱｲﾂ ﾂﾞﾗだぜ～！
どこの世界に
ﾂﾞﾗかぶった英雄が いるか～！
What kind of hero wears a toupee?!
Come up with a better story!!
もうちょっと
上手いｳｿ つきやがれ｡
待ってくれ みんな！
私の話を 聞いてくれ!!
Everyone, wait!! Listen to what I have to say!!
(ｶｲ)みんな～！
Everyone!
(ｶｲ)みんな～!!
Everyone!!
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)すまなかったな…
恥 かかせちまって…｡
Sorry.
We embarrassed you...
悪気は なかった｡ 堪忍してくれ｡
We didn't mean it. Please forgive us.
帰っちまうのか？
(星海坊主)用は 済んだろう｡
Are you leaving?
You're done, right? Sorry I wasn't a good lure.
悪かったな～
いい釣り餌に なってやれなくて｡
もっとも… お前さんのほうは➡
Of course, it was better for you if you didn't lure anyone.
何も 釣れねえほうが
よかったみてえだが？
ﾃﾒｴ…
ｵﾚのﾂﾞﾗ わざと 落としただろう？
You knocked my toupee off on purpose, didn't you?
…あら ﾊﾞﾚてた？
Oh, you noticed. I underestimated you.
おみそれいたしやした｡
Now, my captain will calm down a bit.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)これで 隊長も
少しは おとなしくなるだろう｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)あんな 化け物どもを
相手どって➡
She should give up any ideas of saving the planet from that monster.
星を 救おうなんて考え
捨てちまったほうが いいんだよ｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)この星は 滅ぶ｡
This planet will be destroyed no matter what we do.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)どう あがいてもな…｡
You're all talk. You don't even struggle.
(星海坊主)あがきもしねえﾔﾂが
ぬかすな！
あがいても ﾑﾀﾞなんだよ｡
It's useless to struggle.
…試しに 隊長殿が 敵と憎む➡
If you want to see why, go to the surface and crush that giant bowling ball
地上の あの どでかいﾎﾞｳﾘﾝｸﾞ玉
壊しにいってみるといい｡
my captain hates so much.
んなﾏﾈしたら この星は…➡
If you do that, this planet will still end.
終わるぜ…｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)ありゃあな…
この星 そのものなんだよ｡
It's the planet itself.
Our enemy is the very planet we're standing on.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)ｵﾚたちの敵は
ｵﾚたちが立っている この星…｡
たとえ 倒したとしても
この星は 滅びちまうんだよ｡
Even if we defeated it, this planet will be destroyed.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)制御ｼｽﾃﾑの ｱﾄﾗｽ｡
It's the Atlas control system. It's the life of this planet.
あれは この星の 命なんだ｡
Is this a man-made planet?
人工の星か？ ここは…｡
いや…
中枢を 制御ｼｽﾃﾑに委ねている｡
No... There's a control system at its core.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)もともと この星は➡
This planet was originally unlivable.
人が 住めるような
代物じゃなかった｡
澄んだ空気｡ 肥えた土｡ 清廉な水｡
Clean air, rich soil, and clean water were all made possible because of Atlas.
それらは ｱﾄﾗｽの働きによって
生み出された｡
ｱﾄﾗｽは 星の環境を保つ
浄化ｼｽﾃﾑなんだ｡
Atlas is a purification system that maintains this planet's environment.
It cultivated things that were good for the planet and eliminated things that were bad.
星に
繁栄を もたらすものを育み➡
星に 害をなすものを 排除する｡
But Atlas maintained the planet's balance for only a short while.
だが…
ｱﾄﾗｽが 星の均衡を保てたのも➡
少しの間だった…｡
The population increased, resources were used up,
人口は 増加し
資源は 絞り取られるだけ取られ➡
星の命は 金に変えられた｡
and the life of the planet was turned into money.
いつしか 大地は枯れ
空は よどみ➡
The land soon became barren, the sky became stagnate,
and the planet became a world of sand.
星は 砂の世界へと 姿を変えた｡
わかるだろう？
You know why Atlas revolted against humans, right?
ｱﾄﾗｽが なぜ
人間に 反乱を起こしたのか…｡
ﾔﾂは 人間を 星に 害をなす脅威と
みなしたんだ｡
It sees humans as a harmful threat to the planet.
It considers us as enemies.
ｵﾚたちは 星に 敵と みなされた｡
壊滅した軍部じゃ 表向き｡
Our devastated military said that it was a mysterious invader
made of an unknown material... But there were those who knew.
未知の物質で 構成された
謎の侵略者なんて➡
銘 打っちゃいたが…➡
気づくﾔﾂは 気づいていたさ…｡
黙っていても ｵﾚたちは滅ぶ…｡
We'll be wiped out if we don't do anything.
But even if we fight Atlas and destroy it, this planet will still be wiped out.
だが
戦って ｱﾄﾗｽを破壊したとしても➡
この星は 滅ぶ…｡
ｵﾚたちに残された道は
滅亡の道だけだと…｡
Our only path is the path to extinction.
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)そりゃあ 誰も戦おうなんざ
思わねえはずだ｡
That's why no one wants to fight.
戦ったところで
何も 変わりはしない｡
Even if we did, it wouldn't change anything.
No, even if they did fight Atlas, there's probably no way they could destroy it.
いや… もともと
ｱﾄﾗｽに 刃向かったところで➡
あれを 人の手で破壊することは
不可能だろうしな…｡
戦って 滅ぶより➡
So they've chosen to slowly rot here rather than be wiped out in battle.
ここで ゆっくり腐っていくことを
選んだってのか？
(星海坊主)あの 娘っ子以外は…｡
Aside from that girl...
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)隊長は
滅ぶつもりなんかねえよ｡
My captain has no intention of perishing.
She still hasn't given up hope.
まだ 望みを 捨てちゃいねえ｡
たとえ 一人になっても
戦うだろう…｡
She'll probably fight even if she's alone.
もう つきあいきれねえよ…｡
I can't keep this up any longer.
ｼｪﾙﾀｰを 守ることにもなると
ｹﾞﾘﾗ活動にも つきあってきたが➡
I was helping her with guerrilla attacks to defend the shelter...
戦って 何が 得られる？
But what can I gain by fighting? This planet is no good. I can't live here anymore.
この星は もう ﾀﾞﾒだ…｡
こんなところで 生きていくことは
もう できねえ…｡
勝ったところで
待つのは 滅びのみ…｡
Even if we win, we'll only perish.
隊長は いったい
なんのために 戦いを…｡
What is my captain fighting for?
(ｻｲﾚﾝ)
敵襲だ～!!
It's an enemy attack!
ひぃ～っ！
ﾔﾂらだ！
It's here!
ﾔﾂらが ついに
このｼｪﾙﾀｰを 嗅ぎつけやがった！
It's finally discovered the shelter!!
おしまいじゃ～！
ﾜｼらも ついに おしまいじゃ～!!
It's over!! We're finally finished!!
♪♪～
It's Kai!
あれは… ｶｲだ！
Kai is retaliating by herself!
ｶｲが 一人で 応戦を…！
(星海坊主)何を している？
What are you doing?
なんで 助けにいかねえ？
Why aren't you going to help her?
ｱｲﾂが 何を守るために戦ってるか
わからねえのか？
Don't you know what she's fighting to defend?
ﾑﾀﾞだ…｡
It's hopeless... Even if we fight...
戦ったって… もう…｡
(星海坊主)どうやら
もう 終わってんのは➡
It looks like it's not just the planet that's already finished. It's you.
星じゃなくて…
ﾃﾒｴらのほうらしいな｡
♪♪～
Tsk!
ﾁｯ！
(爆発音)
Captain, hold on!!
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)隊長！
しっかりしろ！ おい！
苗…｡
The seedling...
苗は… 無事か？
Is the seedling all right?
ｺｲﾂは…
こんな乾いた大地に 苗を…｡
She was...
Growing a seedling in such a dry land...
♪♪～
あれは…｡
That's...
♪♪～
It's a rescue convoy!
救護船団！
Yeah! They've finally come for us!
ああ！ ようやく
ｵﾚたちのところにも来やがった！
They said we're the only ones on this planet!
They said they'll let all of us get on!!
この星に残ってるのは
ｵﾚたちだけだって！
全員残らず
乗っけてってくれるってよ！
All right!! We're saved!!
やったぜ～！
ｵﾚたち 助かったんだ～!!
ついに こんな星とも
おさらばだぜ！
We can finally say goodbye to this planet!!
(歓声)
I'm not going.
私は… 行かない｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)たっ 隊長 何を…！
C-Captain, what are you saying?
(ｶｲ)私は この星に残って
最後まで戦うと言ったんだ｡
I said that I'm going to stay on this planet and fight until the end.
What's the point of fighting any longer?
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)これ以上 戦って
何の意味があるんだ？
隊長だって わかってたはずだ！
もう この星は ﾀﾞﾒだって｡
You should already know.
This planet is no good.
ひからびちまって
草も木も生えやしねえ！
It's all dried up. Grass and trees won't grow.
おまけに ｱﾄﾗｽの暴走…！
Furthermore, Atlas has gone haywire.
もう この星じゃ
生きていけないんだよ！
We can't live on this planet anymore!!
逃げてどうする？
逃げ込んだ星を腐らせ➡
What good will come of running away?
Are you going to ruin the next planet you run away and escape to?
また 次の星へ逃げるのか？
Are you going to keep on repeating that?
それを 延々 繰り返すのか？
大地が乾いているなら
水をまけばいい｡
If the land is dry, we can pour water.
花が咲かないなら
種を植えればいい｡
If flowers don't bloom, we can plant seeds.
私たちは これまで
ｱﾄﾗｽに頼りすぎた｡
We've been relying too much on Atlas.
今まで 自分たちの力で➡
Did we ever think of doing something about the planet ourselves?
星をなんとかしようと
したことがあったか？
戦って この星を守ろうと
Have we ever fought to protect this planet?
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)わからんよ… 星なんて
でかい規模のこと ｵﾚには…｡
I don't understand large-scale things like planets.
だが ｵﾚにも 女房 子供…
守らなきゃいけないもんがある｡
But I have a wife and children to protect.
星を捨てようがなんだろうが➡
I have to live even if I have to discard my planet.
それでも
生きてかにゃならねえ…｡
ｱﾝﾀとも 星とも
心中はできねえ… あばよ 隊長｡
I cannot commit suicide with you and this planet.
Farewell, captain.
一人になっちまったな｡
いいんだ｡
You're all alone now.
It's all right.
人は それぞれ
己の定めた戦いをしている｡
Everyone is fighting their own battles.
He's just headed to his.
ｱｲﾂは
自分の戦いに向かっただけだ｡
ｱﾝﾀは どこで戦ってるんだ？
Where are you fighting?
倒せば 星が滅ぶ敵と戦い続け➡
You're continuing to fight an enemy that will destroy the planet if you defeat it.
あげく
星から人間がいなくなっても➡
You won't even quit when everyone is gone from the planet.
戦いをやめようとしない｡
ｱﾝﾀは 何のために戦ってる？
What are you fighting for?
私たちは この星を
ｱﾄﾗｽという鎖で勝手に縛りつけ➡
We've bound this planet with the chains called Atlas and treated it poorly.
思うがままに 酷使し続けてきた｡
それが
使えなくなったからといって➡
Even if it's of no use anymore,
鎖をつけたまま 宇宙の片隅に
放り出すわけにはいかない｡
we can't just fling it into a corner of space chained up.
誰かが 星を… ｱﾄﾗｽの呪縛から
解放してあげなければ…｡
Someone has to release this planet from the curse of Atlas.
それが 滅びにつながるとしても？
滅ばない｡
Even if it leads to its destruction?
It won't be destroyed.
私たちが ｱﾄﾗｽの代わりに
この星を支えれば➡
If we support this planet in place of Atlas, seedlings are sure to grow...
この乾いた大地にも
きっと 苗は育つ｡
In this dry land.
ﾌﾝ… ﾊｯﾊｯﾊｯﾊﾊﾊ…!!
(笑い声)
要するになんだ… ｱﾝﾀ
あきらめの悪い人ってことか？
In other words, you don't give up easily?
負けず嫌いなだけだ｡
戦いから逃げたくない｡
I just hate to lose. I don't want to run away from battle.
生きることは
戦うことだと思っている｡
I think the meaning of living is to fight.
自分の定めた戦いから
背を向ければ 死したも同然｡
If you turn your back on your battles,
you're just as good as dead.
最後まで 人でありたいんだ｡
たとえ明日 星が滅ぶとしても➡
I want to be a good person until the end.
Even if the planet is destroyed tomorrow,
I will not forfeit my honor.
品性は売りたくない｡
最後まで 高潔で美しくありたい｡
I will be noble and beautiful until the end. I will do what I think is right.
自分の正しいと思うことをしたい｡
最後まで 自分に負けたくない｡
I will not lose to myself, even in the end.
似てるな｡
You're just like her.
いや ｵﾚの娘にな｡
いや それとも ｱｲﾂらか…｡
My daughter. Or perhaps them...
ﾌﾝｯ！
悪いな 隊長殿…｡
Sorry, captain.
ｵﾚは ｱﾝﾀ
死なせたくなくなっちまった｡
I don't want you to die.
心配いらねえ
ｱﾝﾀは もう十分に美しい人だよ｡
Don't worry. You're already more than beautiful enough.
お前が 証人になってやりな｡
You can be my witness.
Thanks...
すまねぇ…｡
さっさと連れてけ｡
Take her away.
Umibozu-san, what about you?
星海坊主さん ｱﾝﾀは？
あん？
Huh?
ちょっと ﾂﾞﾗとってくる｡
I'm going to get my toupee.
♪♪～
(星海坊主)神楽ちゃん…｡
Kagura-chan, something's changed in your father.
お父さん どうにも
おかしくなっちゃった｡
昔のｵﾚじゃ考えられねえ
変な扉 開いちゃったなぁ｡
I've opened a strange door that I would've never opened before.
地球に行ってから
おかしくなっちゃったよ｡
Something's happened ever since I went to earth.
Your father... Your father...
お父さんな… お父さん…！
♪♪～
Is going to crush a planet...
(星海坊主)女のために➡
星１個 潰すぞ～!!
for the sake of a woman!!
I'm one hip, bad daddy!
[Note: The term he uses, "Choiwaru Oyaji" is a fashion term used to describe "hip" middle-aged men.]
今はやりの ﾁｮｲ悪親父だぁぁ!!
♪♪～
Keep this a secret from your mother!!
母さんには 内緒だぞぉぉぉ!!
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)何があった？
たった３か月で こんな…｡
What happened?
In just three months...
あの人しかいないだろう｡
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)まさか たった一人で？
It has to be him.
He couldn't have done it by himself...
(ｲﾜﾉﾌ)女 一人のために
星１個 滅ぼした…｡
He destroyed a planet for the sake of a woman.
(ｶｲ)違うさ… あの人には
あの人の戦いがあったんだろう｡
No... He probably has his own battles.
それに 見ろ｡
And, look.
滅んでなんかいない｡
It's not destroyed.
ちゃんと生きてるぞ｡
It's still alive.
♪♪～
＜星海坊主:絶望に
打ちひしがれることがあっても➡
Even if you're crushed by despair...
You must never forget that where there is light,
忘れてはいけない｡
陽あるところに影があるように➡
there are shadows and where there are shadows, there is light.
影あるところに 陽があることを｡
No matter how dark the despair, there is hope shining bright!
絶望の色が 濃ければ濃いほど➡
そこには 強く輝く
光があることを＞
あきらめるな！ 男たちよ！
Men, don't give up!!
No matter how barren you are, you'll grow hair.
どんな荒地にも 必ず毛は生える！
A hair restorer for men who don't give up the fight!! Atlas Neo!
(ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ)あきらめない
戦う男を応援する育毛剤➡
｢ｱﾄﾗｽ NEO｣！
[Atlas Neo]
毛根の栄養を育み➡
[Iyokan Extract]
[(Moisturizer)]
[Tangerine Extract]
[Carrot Extract]
[(Moisturizer)]
[Swertica Japonica Extract]
[(Improves Blood Circulation)]
[Dipotassium Glycyrrhizate]
[(Anti-inflammatory)]
It's a purifying hair restorer that sends nutrients to your hair roots and removes excess oils.
余分な脂を排除する 浄化育毛剤➡
Atlas Neo!!
[Atlas Neo]
｢ｱﾄﾗｽ NEO｣!!
もう ｶﾂﾗとは おさらばだ～!!
Say goodbye to toupees!
(ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ)今 購入すれば➡
[A present for everyone!]
If you order now, you'll get a cell phone strap of the legendary hunter Umibozu's favorite umbrella!
伝説のﾊﾝﾀｰ 星海坊主の➡
愛用 傘ｽﾄﾗｯﾌﾟがもらえる！
(星海坊主)
あきらめるな！ 男たちよ!!
Men, don't give up!!
(新八)どんだけ 長いＣＭだぁ!!
[Odd Jobs Gin]
How long is this commercial?!
You've got to be kidding!
(銀時)ふざけんじゃねえよ!!
30分にわたって 育毛剤のＣＭ!?
A thirty minute hair restorer commercial?!
つうか なんでＣＭ撮ってんだよ
このﾊｹﾞ!!
And why is this baldy in a commercial?!
Give us back our screen time!
ｵﾚたちの出番 返せ!!
(星海坊主)
あきらめるな！ 男たちよ!!
Men, don't give up!
- You're being a pest! Give up already!!
(銀時/新八)しつけえよ！
もう あきらめろ!!
[Preview]
I was quite famous long ago.
I traveled to all the galaxies.
You liar. You're exaggerating, aren't you?
The next episode... "Exaggerate the Tales of Your Exploits by a Third, so Everyone Has a Good Time."
[In the other half, Kagura becomes a mini Gin-san?!
"Men Have a Weakness for Girls Who Sell Flowers and Work in Pastry Shops"]
[Lately, I've been really lucky, so I went to a purification with everyone.]